It’s crazy when you think about all of
the different kinds of foods we eat.
We just swallow and hope
it all works out for the best.
Well, as it turns out,
there are better ways to think about keeping
our bodies humming healthfully along.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we look at the
health effects of food additives.
And in our first story,
NutritionFacts Senior Research
Scientist Dr. Kristine Dennis asks
‘Do the reactions ascribed to
monosodium glutamate (MSG)
represent a menace, myth, or marvel?’
Reducing sodium intake
by 30 percent
could save the lives
of more than 40 million people.
And guess what can reduce
sodium intake
by more than 30 percent
in standard recipes?
Substituting traditional salt
with monosodium glutamate,
commonly known as MSG.
But what about "Chinese
Restaurant Syndrome,"
reported in a 1968 letter
to the New England
Journal of Medicine,
characterized by numbness
on the back of the neck,
general weakness,
and palpitation?
One of the proposed causes
was MSG,
a common seasoning often used
in Chinese cooking.
Since then, MSG has been blamed
for causing
numerous adverse reactions,
including asthma, headache,
and neuropsychiatric disorders.
But is this so-called
monosodium glutamate "allergy"
a menace or a myth?
You don't know
until you put it to the test,
or in this case, many tests.
In a multicenter, double-blind,
placebo-controlled,
multiple-challenge trial of MSG,
130 self-reported
MSG-reactive volunteers
first consumed beverages
containing 5 grams of MSG
or a placebo,
and those who reported
two or more
of 10 different symptoms,
such as flushing or headache,
were then rechallenged
in a dose-response study.
Of the 19 people
who consistently responded
to 5 grams of MSG
mixed in a drink,
once MSG was given in a capsule
(therefore ensuring people
couldn't actually taste
the MSG,
which they could
when it was mixed in a drink),
only two people had reactions.
The researchers noted that
large doses of MSG without food
may result in more symptoms,
but no persistent or serious
effects were observed.
For context,
estimated MSG intakes in the UK
are about 0.58 grams per day,
and in Asian countries,
such as China, Korea,
and Vietnam,
where it is
a more commonly used seasoning,
it ranges from 0.33 grams
per day
to 3.8 grams per day,
which is generally much less
than the massive 5g or greater
single doses provided
in the challenge trials.
Yet, only 2 out of 130 people
who claimed
to be sensitive to MSG
had any more symptoms than
when they just took a placebo.
Given the controversy,
consensus meetings
with scientific experts
convened in 1997
and again in 2007,
and concluded that
MSG was harmless,
and no dietary intake limits
needed to be set.
But, in 2017, the
European Food Safety Authority
reevaluated the safety
of glutamate as a food additive,
and decided
to set a limit of 30 mg
per kilogram of body weight
per day,
which is exceeded by
most people every day.
This limit was based off
a rat study from 1979,
with EFSA citing potential
neurodevelopmental
toxicity concerns.
But even the author
of the original study
says they failed to convincingly
show such an effect.
And given MSG's
salt-reducing benefits,
might it be a-okay
as a much-needed tool
to reduce sodium in foods?
Now, MSG still has sodium;
it's monosodium glutamate,
after all;
with about one third the sodium
of typical table salt.
So, a better salt substitute
would be potassium salt,
potassium chloride,
which has the potential
to save even more lives.
Did you know the consumption of
phosphorus preservatives in junk food,
and injected into meat,
may damage blood vessels,
accelerate the aging process,
and contribute to osteoporosis?
In my video "Treating Kidney
Failure through Diet",
I profiled research suggesting that
the use of plant-based diet
may be helpful for the patients
with kidney failure,
because control of dietary
phosphorus intake
is the lynchpin in the
successful control
of a leading cause of disease and
death in kidney failure patients,
too much phosphorous
in the blood.
But now we're beginning
to realize
that absorbing too much phosphorus
isn't good for anyone.
Having high levels in our
blood has been found
to be an independent predictor
of heart attacks
and mortality in the
general population,
increasing the risk of not
only kidney failure,
but heart failure, heart attacks,
coronary death, and overall death.
Higher phosphate
levels associated
with a significantly
shorter lifespan.
Dietary intake of phosphate
is an important matter
not just for persons with kidney
disease, but for everybody.
It's thought to cause
damage to blood vessels
and accelerate the
aging process,
even potentially
hurting our bones,
contributing to osteoporosis by
disrupting hormonal regulation.
The estimated average
requirement of phosphorus
is less than 600 a day,
but the estimated
average intake
is nearly twice that
in the United States.
How do we stay away
from the stuff?
If you look at
nutrient tables,
it looks like many plant foods
have as much phosphorous
as many animal foods,
So why are plant-based
diets so effective
in treating kidney
failure patients?
Because most of the
phosphorus in plant foods
is found in the
form of phytic acid,
which we don't digest,
so the bioavailability
of plant phosphates
is usually less than 50%.
See, only a third to a half of plant
phosphorus may be absorbable,
whereas most animal products
are all up around 75%.
So when you adjust
for how much
actually gets
into our system
you see plant foods
are better.
It's like the absorption of
heme and non-heme iron,
our body can protect
itself from absorbing
too much plant-based iron,
but can't stop excess
blood-based,
or heme iron
from animals
slipping through
the intestinal wall.
The worst kind
of phosphorus,
absorbed nearly 100%,
are phosphate additives
added, for example,
to cola drinks.
Why would they
do that?
Otherwise cola drinks
would be black.
Without the
added phosphate,
there would be so many
glycotoxins produced
that the beverage would
turn pitch black.
Thus, cola drinks owe their
brown color to phosphate.
Phosphate additives play an
especially important role
in the meat industry, where they
are used as preservatives,
for the same reason – to enhance
a meat products color.
Just like the dairy industry
adds aluminum to cheese,
meat and poultry
is "enhanced"
by injecting it
with phosphates.
If you look at meat industry
trade journals
and can get past all
the macabre ads
for head dropping robots
for the kill floor
and foot chopper-offers,
you'll see all these ads
for injection machines.
Why?
Because of increased
profitability.
Enhanced meats have better
color and less purge.
Purge is a term used to
describe the liquid
that seeps from
flesh as it ages.
Many consumers find
this unattractive
and so the industry
views it as a win-win.
When you inject chicken
with phosphates
the consumer benefits through
the perception of enhanced quality,
and the processor benefits
from increased yield
because they just pumped
it up with water
and they sell it
by the pound.
The problem is that it can
boost phosphorus levels
in meat nearly 70%,
a real and insidious danger
for kidney patients,
but now we know it's
a danger for all.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
As always, all proceeds from
book sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.